Guide to the James McMurtry Accessions
The Wittliff Collections
James McMurtry Accessions
1987-2015
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
McMurtry, James (1962)
UPWC.19011
3.5 Linear Feet
4 boxes
Texas singer/songwriter, James McMurtry's archive includes original notepads and loose pages of lyric composition. Albums represented include Too Long in the Wasteland (1989); Candyland (1992); Where'd You Hide the Body (1995); Walk Between the Raindrops (1998); Saint Mary's Wood (2002); Live in Aught-Three (2004); Childish Things (2005); Just Us Kids (2008); and Complicated Game (2015).
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchases, 2019, 2020
Biographical Note
James McMurtry was born March 18, 1962, in Fort Worth, Texas and raised in Leesburg, Virginia. He began writing songs during his teens, occasionally performing them in Tucson, while attending the University of Arizona where he studied English and Spanish. He returned to Texas soon after, and made his Kerrville Folk Festival debut in 1987. Around this time, John Mellencamp was starring in a film written by McMurtry's father, Larry McMurtry, and after hearing James' demo tape, signed on to produce his first album, Too Long in the Wasteland (1989), which achieved critical success. Later albums include Candyland (1992); Where'd You Hide the Body (1995); Walk Between the Raindrops (1998); Saint Mary's Wood (2002); Live in Aught-Three (2004); Childish Things (2005); Just Us Kids (2008); Complicated Game (2015); and The Hourses and the Hounds (2021).
Scope and Contents
Texas singer/songwriter, James McMurtry's archive includes original notepads and loose pages of lyric composition. Albums represented include Too Long in the Wasteland (1989); Candyland (1992); Where'd You Hide the Body (1995); Walk Between the Raindrops (1998); Saint Mary's Wood (2002); Live in Aught-Three (2004); Childish Things (2005); Just Us Kids (2008); and Complicated Game (2015).
Index Terms
Subjects
Popular music -- Writing and publishing; Musicians -- Texas
- Accession 2019-2011
  Abstract
  This archival accession of singer/songwriter, James McMurtry includes original notepads and loose pages of lyric composition. Albums represented include Too Long in the Wasteland (1989); Candyland (1992); Where'd You Hide the Body (1995); Walk Between the Raindrops (1998); Saint Mary's Wood (2002); Live in Aught-Three (2004); Childish Things (2005); Just Us Kids (2008); and Complicated Game (2015).
  The collection arrived in 3 boxes with little discernable order. Box 1 was labeled "Wasteland-Candyland;" Box 2 was labeled "Candyland-St. Mary;" and Box 3 was unlabeled. Each box contained yellow legal pads of song lyric compositions, as well as many loose pages of song lyrics in varying stages of completion.
  The 40 notepads in this accession are loosely arranged according to album, identified by either the cover song on the top sheet of the pad or by other songs included in it. In cases where no song could be identified, the notepads are identified by the box they arrived in. There is no order to the approximately 1000 loose pages of song lyrics; they are simply filed according to the box they arrived in, and kept in the original order.
  Also included in the accession are photographs and negatives including the original negatives for the Too Long in the Wasteland album cover and several black and white performance photos. There is also some publicity clippings, a few business records, flyers, and some Lonesome Dove production records.
  - Files, 1987-2002
    - Business records: Schedule for Floore's Country Store, 2003; Fish & Richardson, 2010; Missouri tax form, 2002 (Box 2940, Folder 1)
    - Publicity and clippings, 1987-1989 (Box 2940, Folder 2)
    - Flyers: With Tish Hinojosa "don't ever change;" Leon Springs Café (multiple) (Box 2940, Folder 3)
    - Lonesome Dove: shooting schedule, memos (Box 2940, Folder 4)
  - Photographs and Negatives, 1987-2008
    Note from McMurtry
    "I think Columbia records probably owns the rights to the entire Wasteland shoot. They did full buyouts back then. Columbia did not fund the neon Candyland shoots. I paid for those and Columbia rejected them. There are some black and white prints from the Live in Aught Three cover shoot taken at the long gone Zephyr in Salt Lake City. Alan Pogue took those, ball cap turned backwards, Farmer's Daughter T-shirt., exit sign. I think his office is called Texas Center for Documentary Photography."
    - Publicity photo, Leon Springs by Kathleen Hudson, 1987; 13 performance photographs (8 x 10); "Box Blind, Archer County, 2008" (4 x 6) (Box 2940, Folder 5)
    - Color negatives from Too Long in the Wasteland cover shoot, circa 1989 (Box 2940, Folder 6)
    - Color negatives and 1 print of portrait with neon art by photographer Smiley N. Pool [possibly intended for Candyland cover], 1991 (Box 2940, Folder 7)
      "Neon House installation for Smiley Poole, original "Candyland" shoot was by Ben Livingston of Austin. I think his business was called Benneon. Neon band, that I had hoped to use for the back cover of Candyland was in a studio owned by a photographer named Bechtolt(I think). Studio was on 6th Avenue in Manhattan not far north of Grammercy Park. My friend, Keith McDonald, who shot the "Wasteland" cover, was Bechtolt's assistant and shot the photos of the neon band."
    - Slides, negatives, and contact sheet for photo shoot at a dam (Box 2940, Folder 8)
    - Color negative strips for portraits (Box 2940, Folder 9-10)
    - Proof for Walk Between the Raindrops; Candyland CD box (Box 2940, Folder 11)
      Related Materials
      Mock-up for Candyland cover featuring Smiley Pool's photographs are in on-going Texas Music box 2499
  - Lyrics – Notepads
    Arrangement
    The 40 notepads in this accession are loosely arranged according to album, identified by either the cover song on the top sheet of the pad or by other songs included in it. In cases where no song could be identified, the notepads are identified by the box they arrived in.
    - Too Long in the Wasteland, 1989
      - Includes "Terry" and "Angeline" (Too Long in the Wasteland) (Box 2941, Folder 1)
      - Cover song "Shining Eyes" (Too Long in the Wasteland) (Box 2941, Folder 2)
      - Cover song "Song for a Deckhand's Daughter" (Too Long in the Wasteland) (Box 2941, Folder 3)
      - Includes "I'm Not From Here" (Too Long in the Wasteland) (Box 2941, Folder 4)
      - Cover song "Crazy Wind" (Too Long in the Wasteland) (Box 2941, Folder 5)
    - Candyland, 1992
      - 3 notepads including "Hands Like Rain" (Candyland); 2nd includes song list for Too Long in the Wasteland (Box 2941, Folder 6)
      - Cover song "Candyland" (Candyland) (Box 2941, Folder 7)
      - 2 notepads including "Save Yourself" (Candyland) (Box 2941, Folder 8)
      - Includes "Storekeeper" (Candyland); mention of Lonesome Dove music (Box 2941, Folder 9)
    - Where'd You Hide the Body, 1995
      - Includes "Off and Running" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 10)
      - Cover song "Fuller Brush Man" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 11)
      - Cover song "Rachel's Song" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 12)
      - 3 notepads including "Down Across the Delaware" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 13)
      - Cover song "One More Winter" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 14)
      - 2 notepads including "Melinda" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 15)
      - Cover song "Right Here Now" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 16)
      - 2 notepads including "Every Little Bit Counts" (Where'd You Hide the Body) (Box 2941, Folder 17)
    - Saint Mary of the Woods, 2002
      - Cover song "Lobo Town" (Saint Mary of the Woods) (Box 2941, Folder 18)
      - Cover song "Saint Mary of the Woods" (Saint Mary of the Woods) (Box 2941, Folder 19)
    - Live in Aught-Three, 2004
      - 2 notepads including "Lights of Cheyenne" (Live in Aught-Three) (Box 2941, Folder 20)
    - Childish Things, 2005
      - Cover song "Bad Enough" (Childish Things) (Box 2941, Folder 21)
      - Includes "Memorial Day" (Childish Things) (Box 2941, Folder 22)
      - Cover song "Charlemagne's Home Town" (Childish Things) (Box 2941, Folder 23)
    - Just Us Kids, 2008
      - Cover song "Fine Line Road" (Just Us Kids) (Box 2941, Folder 24)
      - Cover song "You'd a Though (Leonard Cohen Must Die) (Just Us Kids) (Box 2941, Folder 25)
    - Complicated Game, 2015
      - Cover song "Deaver's Crossing" (Complicated Game) (Box 2941, Folder 26)
      - Cover song "Cutter" (Complicated Game) (Box 2941, Folder 27)
    - Unidentified Notepads
      - Unidentified, includes song "Haskell Country" from "Wasteland-Candyland" box (Box 2942, Folder 1)
      - 4 unidentified notepads from "Wasteland-Candyland" box (Box 2942, Folder 2)
      - 5 unidentified notepads from "Candyland-St. Mary" box (Box 2942, Folder 3)
  - Lyrics – Loose pages
    There is no order to the approximately 1000 loose pages of song lyrics; they are simply filed according to the box they arrived in, and kept in the original order.
    - "Wasteland-Candyland" Box (Approximately 178 pages)
      - 18 loose pages of lyrics not from yellow notepads (Box 2942, Folder 4)
      - Approximately 70 loose pages of lyrics (1 of 2) (Box 2942, Folder 5)
      - Approximately 90 loose pages of lyrics (2 of 2) (Box 2942, Folder 6)
    - "Candyland-St. Mary" Box (Approximately 626 pages)
      - Approximately 70 loose pages of lyrics (1 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 7)
      - Approximately 80 loose pages of lyrics (2 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 8)
      - Approximately 75 loose pages of lyrics (3 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 9)
      - Approximately 78 loose pages of lyrics (4 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 10)
      - Approximately 78 loose pages of lyrics (5 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 11)
      - Approximately 85 loose pages of lyrics (6 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 12)
      - Approximately 80 loose pages of lyrics (7 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 13)
      - Approximately 80 loose pages of lyrics (8 of 8) (Box 2942, Folder 14)
    - Untitled Box 3 (Approximately 150 pages)
      - Loose pages of lyrics not from yellow pads; recording and track sheets (Box 2942, Folder 15)
      - Approximately 50 loose pages of lyrics (1 of 2) (Box 2942, Folder 16)
      - Approximately 50 loose pages of lyrics (2 of 2) (Box 2942, Folder 17)
      - Non lyric writing (5 pages) (Box 2942, Folder 18)
- Accession 2020-055
  Additional sheets of lyric compositions from singer/songwriter, James McMurtry. Song titles are identified when possible, otherwise they are listed according to their opening line. Many of the legal sized yellow notebook pages are crumpled and have remnants of scotch tape. There are a handful white chord progression sheets – possibly done by David Grissom.
  - Chord progressions for "Jackie," "OP," "If it Don't Bleed," and "Glasses." (Box 3502, Folder 1)
  - Lyrics
    - "Blackberry Winter" includes chord progression sheet (Box 3502, Folder 2)
    - "Decent Man" includes chord progression sheet (Box 3502, Folder 3)
    - "She Loves Me" released on Complicated Game (2015) (Box 3502, Folder 4)
    - "Vaquero" includes chord progression sheet. Song in memory of Bill Wittliff (Box 3502, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Lyrics – listed by opening line
    - Notepad and loose sheets - unidentified (Box 3502, Folder 6)
    - "Half a section in the short grass…" (Box 3502, Folder 7)
    - "I was thinking 'bout you crossing Southern Alberta…" (Box 3502, Folder 8)
    - "The phone's on the dash…" (Box 3502, Folder 9)
    - "She woke up mad…" or "Honeymoon's over…" (Box 3502, Folder 10)
    - "Talking to the wallpaper…" (Box 3502, Folder 11)
    - "We got an operation going on…" (Box 3502, Folder 12)
    - "When the white oak leaves are whirling…" (Box 3502, Folder 13)
    - "Your bags are packed…" or "I don't know what went wrong…" (Box 3502, Folder 14)